<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<sect1 id="sesame-integration" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <title>Sesame</title>
    
    <para>The RDFBean sesame module depends currently on Sesame 2.7.6. <emphasis>It is change from past where previous versions 
    of RDFBean depended on Sesame 3.0 alpha.</emphasis></para>
      
   	<para>Sessame 2.7 support is provided via the rdfbean-sesame2 module.</para>   
   	
   	<para>Sessame 3.0 alpha support is provided via the rdfbean-sesame3 module.</para>   
      
    <para>From version 1.7, RDFBean implements three main Sesame Repository backends : MemoryRepository, NativeRepository, HTTPRepository.</para>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>MemoryRepository</title>
      
      <para>MemoryRepository is an Repository implementation wrapping the Sesame MemoryStore. 
      The configuration options are the data dir for File based data persistence and sesameInference
      for turning on the Sesame level RDF Schema inference.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>NativeRepository</title>
      
      <para>NativeRepository wraps the Sesame NativeStore and has the mandatory configuration attribute
      dataDir for the location of the data directory and sesameInference for turning on Seame inference.</para>
      
      <para>NativeRepository is slower for small amounts of triples than the MemoryRepository, but scales
      better with higher amounts of triples</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>HTTPRepository</title>
      
      <para>HTTPRepository is an Repository implementation wrapping the Sesame HTTPRepository. 
      This allow RDFBean users to use remote repositories like OWLIM etc.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Custom Sesame repository</title>
      
      <para>To use other Sesame repositories or further customize the usage of MemoryStore and NativeStore 
      create a subclass of AbstractSesameRepository.</para>
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Declaring inital data</title>
      
      <para>To declare initial data for a Sesame based repository you can use the setSources method like this :</para>
      
<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[         
repository.setSources(
  new RDFSource("classpath:/test.ttl", Format.TURTLE, TEST.NS),
  new RDFSource("classpath:/foaf.rdf", Format.RDFXML, FOAF.NS)
);    
]]>
</programlisting>

      <para>The parameters for RDFSource are the location of the data as an URL expression, the format of the data
      and the target context in the Repository.</para>        
    
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
      <title>Inferencing</title>
      
      <para>
        RDF Schema inferencing via ForwardChainingRDFSInferencer turned out to be quite slow, 
        so we are providing lightweight inferencing for subClassOf, subPropertyOf expansions on 
        RDFBean level.
      </para>  
      
      <para>
        Sesame repository level inferencing is disabled by default, but can be activated like this:
      </para>

<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[   
MemoryRepository repository = new MemoryRepository();
repository.setSesameInference(true);
]]>
</programlisting>        

      <para>   
        Subtypes and subproperties are provided to the Repository level via the Ontology interface. 
        The Ontology can either be populated via the Repository itself or via the Configuration.
      </para>

      <para>
        The Repository based population is suitable for cases, where the ontology is defined in the
        repository data itself and the Configuration based approach for cases where it isn't.
      </para> 
      
      <para>The Repository based Ontology is the default option and the Configuration based
        Repository can be used like this :</para>
        
<programlisting language="java">
<![CDATA[    
Configuration configuration = new DefaultConfiguration(classes);
Ontology ontology = new ConfigurationOntology(configuration);
MemoryRepository repository = new MemoryRepository();
repository.setOntology(ontology);
repository.initialize();
]]>
</programlisting>            
    
    </sect2>
    
</sect1>    